Guide to the James R. Cox Papers, 1904-1950, (bulk 1923-1950) AIS.1969.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
James R. Cox Papers
1904-1950
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Cox, James R.
AIS.1969.05
4.38 Linear Feet
James R. Cox, a son of a Pittsburgh millworker, was a Pittsburgh Catholic priest and a political and social activist. The collection contains Father Cox's diary (1904), scrapbooks of newspaper clippings (1923-1951), 426 photographs, and 28 audio cassettes of radio broadcasts, sermons, and hymns (1944-50). Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
Biography
James R. Cox was born in 1886. He was a Pittsburgh Catholic priest, political and social activist, and the son of a millworker. During the Depression he organized a food-relief program and helped the homeless and unemployed find shelter. In January 1932 Cox led a march of 15,000-20,000 unemployed Pennsylvanians to Washington, D.C. He hoped that a demonstration of the unemployed in Washington would stir Congress to start a public works program. This did not happen at the time, but the march sparked the formation of the Jobless Party in Pittsburgh. The Jobless Party supported government public works and labor unions, and spread to other major cities. James Cox became the Jobless Party's first presidential candidate but in September 1932 Cox pulled out of the election giving his support to the Democratic ticket and Franklin Roosevelt. This effectively led to the demise of the Jobless Party.
After the presidential election of 1932 Cox continued his relief work and was a member of the Pennsylvania Commission for the Unemployed. In the mid-thirties Roosevelt appointed him to the state recovery board of the National Recovery Administration. James Cox became known as Pittsburgh's "Pastor of the Poor."
For information on Cox's presidential campaign see Andrew I. Krupnick's "Father Cox's Campaign for the Presidency of the United States [in 1932; a diary]." (ais MS 5)
Scope and Content Notes
The James R. Cox Papers include a diary (1904), scrapbooks of newspaper clippings (1923-1951), 426 photographs, and 28 audiocassettes of radio broadcasts, sermons, and hymns (1944-50).
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Earl J. Cox, sister-in-law of Father James Cox, February 21, 1969.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions from this collection are available at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/father-cox-papers.
Previous Citation
James R. Cox Papers, 1923-1950, AIS.1969.05, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Priests -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Depressions -- 1929 -- United States; Unemployed -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Economic conditions; Unemployed -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; United States -- Politics and government -- 1929-1933; Personal papers; Social action; Labor; Cox, James R.; Jobless Party (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Diary and Manuscripts, 1904-1936; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains a diary, transcript of an interview, manuscript, and certificates.
  - Diary, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview with Father Cox, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Holy Land Pictures - Manuscript to accompany travel film, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificates (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Newspaper Clipping Scrapbooks, 1923-1973; II.
  Series II includes photocopies of clippings pertaining to Father Cox, the Jobless Party, Marches, Pilgrimages, and other events. Also included are articles written about Father Cox and his various causes.
  - 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - October 7, 1924-December 31, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1927-1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1951-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Odyssey of Pittsburgh's Father Cox, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Father Cox's Own Story of Jobless March to Capital, c. 1920's (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Original Scrapbooks (Box 2, Folder 4)
- St. Patrick's Church, 1925-1934; III.
  Series III includes a journal and a bulletin from St. Patrick's Church, Pittsburgh, PA.
  - Clothes Room Journal, 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photographs, 1923-1950; IV.
  Series IV consists of 426 photographs of Father Cox, his family, groups of people, pilgrimages, and other scenes. They are arranged by subject.
  - Father Cox (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cox Family (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Group Photos (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - John Flaherty (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Great Depression (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Funeral Procession (not Father Cox's) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jobless Party (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Old St. Patrick's (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Passion Play (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pilgrimages (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sports (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Group Photos (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Negatives (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Oversized Items, V.
  Series V consists of oversized items including large photographic prints, newspaper clippings, pastel drawings, and sketches of Father Cox, church services, baseball teams, and various groups of people.
  - Oversized Items (Map-case 7-1)
- Audiocassettes, 1944-1950; VI.
  Series VI consists of 28 audiocassettes, copied from phonodiscs, of radio broadcasts, sermons, and hymns given by Father Cox. Some of the cassettes do not have titles and are listed only by date.
  - no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 1-2)
  - October 16, 1944 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 3)
  - October 16, 1944; October 23, 1944 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 4)
  - October 23, 1944 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 5)
  - Sermon for November 21, November 15, 1944 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 6)
  - December 11, 1944 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 7)
  - January 8, 1945 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 8)
  - "Do Not Play on Air", no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 9)
  - June 13, 1950 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 10)
  - no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 11-13)
  - May 7, 1945 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 14)
  - July 17, 1945 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 15)
  - State Guard, June 11, 1945 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 16)
  - Gossiptown, June 11, 1945 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 16)
  - Sermon for July 12 and Sermon for July 14, no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 17)
  - Why Pilgrimages and Friends on Pilgrimages, no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 18)
  - Announcements, no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 19)
  - January 23, 1947 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 20-21)
  - no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 22)
  - Indiantown Gap, May 28, 1945 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 23)
  - no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 24)
  - August 5, 1948 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 25)
  - Interviewing Hildegarde, no date (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 25)
  - August 5, 1948; July 15, 1948 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 26)
  - July 15, 1948 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 27)
  - 25th Anniversary Broadcast, WJAS, November 22, 1950 (Map-case 7-1, Cassette 28)